טוב, Tov, today's דף daf is קיג Kuf Yud Gimmel and we
move here from מצוות, mitzvot, I mean it's really a nice part
of the מסכת masechet where we're dealing with some מצוות mitzvot in
the תורה Torah relating to governing these relationships. So before we had
the employee, employer employee and today what we're doing is we're having
the issues about the borrower and the lender. I mean we know
we had a whole פרק perek about charging interest, but here we
get to beyond the interest issue, the basic ways in which a
borrower could sort of exert his authority or exert his power over
the lender. And actually what I wanted to start with, I actually
forgot, let me just get a רמב"ם Rambam because the רמב"ם Rambam
has a nice listing of it. If
I wanted to start with the פסוקים psukim in the תורה Torah
that relate to these מצוות mitzvot because it gets a little confusing.
The גמרא Gemara does not do, I mean the רמב"ם Rambam in
the beginning of הלכות מלווה ולווה Hilchos Malveh VeLoveh does a nice
listing of the מצוות, mitzvot, but the גמרא Gemara does not and
sometimes it gets a little confusing, what are all the different מצוות
mitzvot associated with this? Okay, so let me just sort of show
you, let me just sort of put some of this up on
the board here.
Okay, so we have the following.
Okay, so the פסוק pasuk says like this:
So we had לא תעשוק שכיר עני ואביון, lo tashok sechir ani
ve-evyon, that's what we dealt with before, okay, which is the idea
of not paying on time. This is in דברים כד. Devarim Chaf
Daled. And then we have כד יז: Chaf Daled Yud Zayin: לא
תטה משפט גר יתום ולא תחבול בגד אלמנה. lo tateh mishpat ger
yatom velo tachavol beged almanah.
Okay,
so one is לא תחבול בגד אלמנה. lo tachavol beged almanah.
Do not take as collateral the garment of an אלמנה. almanah. Okay,
then the תורה Torah says, that's one
פסוק. pasuk. Okay,
then, hold on, going on,
okay, I'm sorry, earlier it said, I jumped ahead, earlier it said:
כי תשה ברעך משאת מאומה לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו. ki
tasheh vere'acha mashat me'umah lo tavo el beito la'avot avoto. כי תשה
ברעך, ki tasheh vere'acha,
if you are lending money, if you've lent money
to your friend, לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו.
lo
tavo el beito la'avot avoto.
Do not enter into his house to take the collateral. Okay, בחוץ
תעמוד. bachutz ta'amod. Stay outside. והאיש אשר אתה נושה בו יוציא אליך
את העבוט החוצה. veha'ish asher attah nosheh bo yotzi elecha et ha'avot
hachutzah. He can,
he'll bring the collateral to you. ואם איש עני הוא לא תשכב
בעבוטו. ve'im ish ani hu lo tishkav ba'avoto. ואם איש עני הוא
לא תשכב בעבוטו.
ve'im ish ani hu lo
tishkav ba'avoto.
השב תשיב לו את העבוט כבוא השמש ושכב בשלמתו וברכך והיה לך
צדקה לפני ה' אלוהיך.
hashev tashiv lo et ha'avot kevo hashemesh
veshachav besalmato uverachecha vehayah lecha tzedakah lifnei Hashem Elokecha. Alright, השב תשיב,
hashev tashiv, השב תשיב העבוט כבוא
השמש.
hashev
tashiv ha'avot kevo hashemesh.
Okay,
so right here in these פסוקים, psukim, these are not the whole
ones, but let's talk for a moment about what we have in
these פסוקים. psukim. This is דברים כד. Devarim Chaf Daled. First we
have if you're dealing with an אלמנה, almanah, don't take her garment.
Okay, now is it limited to a, I doubt myself, alright, so
is it, okay, so the way the רמב"ם Rambam says it, for
example, this מצווה mitzvah of the אלמנה, almanah, the רמב"ם Rambam says,
hold on, okay, שלא יחבול אלמנה, shelo yachavol almanah,
it's not just בגד אלמנה, beged almanah, right? Do not be חובל
chovel any אלמנה, almanah, in the, I'll just read you again from
the רמב"ם, Rambam, this is מלווה ולווה. Malveh VeLoveh. אלמנה בין שהיא
עניה בין שהיא עשירה אין ממשכנין אותה. almanah bein she'aniyah bein she'ashirah
ein memashkenin otah. You don't take collateral, לא בשעת הלוואה ולא שלא
בשעת הלוואה, lo besha'at halva'ah velo shelo besha'at halva'ah, not at the
time of the loan, not after the time of the loan, okay,
etc. etc. So one מצווה mitzvah by an אלמנה almanah is you
don't take any collateral. Okay, we're not going to really deal with
an אלמנה, almanah, at least not directly, but that's like if it's
an אלמנה, almanah, you can never take collateral. Now by the way
I should mention, all these פסוקים psukim about taking a collateral, returning
collateral, רמב"ם Rambam applies them even to a case where the collateral
is being taken at the time of the loan. So he says
you can't even ask collateral from an אלמנה almanah at the time
that you're lending the money. ראב"ד Ra'avad disagrees and ראב"ד, Ra'avad, because
no, the collateral is I lent you money without collateral, you're not
paying up, and now I'm going to either, either through seizing it
with force or through urging you or through getting בית דין beis
din involved, I'm now going to come and take collateral from you
because you're not paying up to ensure that you will pay up.
Okay, so that's שלא בשעת הלוואה. shelo besha'at halva'ah. So רמב"ם Rambam
says that all these מצוות mitzvot apply in both cases, ראב"ד Ra'avad
disagrees. ראב"ד Ra'avad says that collateral given at the time of a
loan is not considered... really like collateral, it's more like a business
transaction. You're lending me money, I'm giving you this to hold, we're
all sort of on equal footing. It's not the same as coming
into my house and seizing it after the loan has been made.
I might really reframe it not so much as business transaction as
it's not so much of the power issue. See part of the
problem here with all of this is that if you lend me
money like עבד לוה לאיש מלוה, Eved Loveh Le'ish Malveh, the גמרא
Gemara quotes the פסוק, Pasuk, right? I exert this power over you,
this control over you. You're indebted to me, literally indebted to me,
right? So the problem is the abuse of that power relationship. At
the time when we're actually lending, I'm lending you the money, there's
no, I mean true you need the money, you're in need of
it, so there still is something there, but I haven't yet lent
you the money. I don't yet have that power relationship over you.
So at that stage you give me collateral or whatever, there's nothing
problematic about it. But after I've lent you the money, I'm now
going to exert the collateral from you because of the power I
have over you, that's more of the sort of concern of the
פסוקים Pesukim here. So there is that debate of רמב"ם Rambam and
ראב"ד Raavad whether these issues about taking collateral etcetera apply even at
the time of the loan or only not at the time of
the loan. But one thing is by an אלמנה, Almanah, whether she's
rich or poor, you cannot take collateral, we don't limit it to
בגד. Beged. Okay? We're going to put that aside because that's a
special case of an אלמנה. Almanah. Here you have the following פסוקים,
Pesukim, which is when if you lend money do not enter his
house to take his collateral. Okay? So this is the person could
be wealthy. Okay? I lent you a thousand dollars, I lent you
ten thousand dollars, you're a millionaire but you're not giving me the
money and I need to get some insurance that I'm going to
get the money. This is not about an עני. Ani. An עני
Ani is the next פסוק. Pasuk. Even if you're rich I cannot,
and this is clearly now taking collateral after the money has been
lent, right? Because it's now I'm going to enter into your house
in order because I'm concerned about my loan and take that collateral.
I am not allowed to forcefully enter into or not even forcefully,
I mean you could invite me in, but I cannot basically like
enter in, I have to ask you to come out and to
give me the collateral outside. And that really is totally about that
power relationship of the, what do you call it, of the
of the lender and the borrower. And I can't exert that over
you, exert my power over you, invade your home in order to
take, I'm entitled to protect my loan, you have to bring it
out to me, but I can't invade your home. Now by the
way I should say, you know, many years ago I heard מנחם
אלון Menachem Elon speak about, you know, about משפט עברי. Mishpat Ivri.
And the whole משפט עברי Mishpat Ivri enterprise is an interesting one
because you're trying to take הלכה, Halacha, you're not calling it הלכה,
Halacha, but our הלכתי Halachic heritage and bridge the gap between that
and a sort of democratic system, right? And הלכה Halacha isn't always
democracy and protects, doesn't always protect rights of individuals the same way
modern democracies does, you know, religious pluralism, all those types of things
etcetera. Besides that though, הלכה Halacha is based on a sense of
obligation whereas contemporary law, democracy, not democracy but whatever, modern sort of
you know legal thinking since the enlightenment, the rights of man is
based on a sense of rights. So I heard that you know
מנחם אלון Menachem Elon was once saying, well you see since the
תורה Torah doesn't let you enter into the person's house to forcefully
take your
collateral, you see that the תורה Torah believes in the right to
privacy, you know like the right against search and seizure, the right
of to invade my home. So I got really upset and I
said I don't see any right in the פסוק. Pasuk. I see
an obligation, a prohibition, right? Now obviously and that's number one. So
it's just even if it's true that what the תורה Torah is
concerned of is protecting your right to be safe in your home
and to not have your home invaded, it's different if you frame
it as a right of privacy or a prohibition or an obligation
on others. Even if we're talking about the same phenomenon, there is
a difference. But beyond which the question is are we talking about
the same phenomenon? Because is this about your right in general? Like
let's say I haven't lent you money, okay, and I just burst
into your house. I have not violated this פסוק Pasuk because this
פסוק Pasuk is specifically because of the power relationship that exists between
the lender and the borrower. It's not a general right that I
have to not have people invade my home. Okay? So that's this
פסוק. Pasuk. Now we'll see a little bit about this whether this
applies to people other than the borrower, other than the lender later.
Now if he's that's anybody, if he's poor though then simply you
have to make sure that you don't hold on to his collateral
when he needs it and you have to return it to him
when he needs it which then raises the problem so what's going
to pressure him to pay up if he gets to use it
whenever he needs it? Okay? But that's he doesn't have it
with them all the time.
Exactly. So we'll see about that. But that's a special case of
a poor person. If he's rich you don't go into his home,
he delivers the collateral, you hold on to it. If he's poor
then even after he's delivered the collateral, if he needs... needs the
collateral, you have to return it on a regular basis, okay? Return
it when he needs it. לא תשכב בעבטו, Lo tishkav ba'avoto, return
it to him; if he needs it at night, then you return
it at night; if he needs it at day, you return it
at day, and we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara.
Yes. I don't quite understand what you mean, because it seems to
me that although you could argue with it, but you could make
a case that there's an implied right of privacy, of a קל
וחומר; kal v'chomer; if this guy can't come into your home, then
certainly somebody who doesn't have, you don't have some obligation...
Right. So that's what, so that's what מנחם אלון Menachem Elon said
back to me, okay? But A, I don't know that that's true,
it's a, it's a possible, I don't see that, I see you
could make it, but I would still say even if, we'll see
in the גמרא Gemara about this, related issues, but even if that
were true, I still think that we have to acknowledge when we
are translating איסורים isurim and חיובים chiyuvim into rights. You know, it's
a different mentality, the תורה's Torah sort of way of conceptualizing our
religious legal obligations and the sort of Western, you know, enlightenment way
of conceptualizing it, even if we're talking about the same phenomenon. Okay,
but that's anyway a later, a different discussion. Okay, so those are
some of the basic מצוות. mitzvot. Now, oh, I'm sorry, we have
to mention two others that are important, okay? And that is לא
יחבול ריחיים ורכב. lo yachavor reychayim varachev. Where's that פסוק? pasuk? Hold
on. Yeah. I know where, I'm just trying to remember where it
is.
Hold on, let's use the רמב״ם. Rambam. Is it כד ו? chaf-daled
vav?
Is it, am I here?
It's in the same place.
דברים כד. Devarim chaf-daled. Yeah, it is in the same place. It
is in כד. chaf-daled. They're all in כד. chaf-daled. לא יחבול ריחיים
ורכב כי נפש הוא חובל. lo yachavor reychayim varachev ki nefesh hu
chovel. לא יחבול ריחיים ורכב כי נפש הוא חובל. lo yachavor reychayim
varachev ki nefesh hu chovel. Okay, so that is, do not take
something that is, when the way it gets interpreted because of
נפש, nefesh, something that is necessary for somebody's livelihood, sustaining themselves and
so on. Basically. Now, the question is even for the rich maybe,
but you know there's an interesting question, let's say I've got ten
ריחיים reychayims and they're all in use. So on the one hand
they're all ריחיים reychayims so I'm making a profit off of them.
You know, what exactly falls into this category? But it does not
say for an עני. ani. It just says לא יחבול ריחיים ורכב,
lo yachavor reychayim varachev, okay?
And the way, as the רמב״ם Rambam phrases it, שלא יחבול כלים
שעושים בהם אוכל נפש, shelo yachavor kelim sheosin bahem ochel nefesh, right?
Food-based types of כלים, kelim, נפש, nefesh, אוכל נפש, ochel nefesh, okay?
So that gets translated as כלים שעושה kelim sheoseh and then you
know what means שעושה אוכל נפש? sheoseh ochel nefesh? If I'm, if
they're עושה אוכל נפש oseh ochel nefesh because I have a whole
factory of them and I'm
making a profit? Okay, but anyway that is also not limited to
the poor. So the one thing that is limited to the poor
is the returning of the עבות. avot. All right, those are the
basic מצוות mitzvot around borrower and lender within this context and the
last thing I should say and that gets into the power issue
and this won't be discussed in our גמרא Gemara is
it's the פסוק pasuk about לא תהיה לו כנושה. lo tihiyeh lo
k'nosheh. Just trying to remind myself where it
is, looking in the רמב״ם. Rambam.
משפטים. Mishpatim.
משפטים שם. Mishpatim sham. Where's שם? sham?
Hold on, this is all conceptual. But how do you take somebody's
millstone?
Yeah. Okay, anyway, anyway, back in משפטים Mishpatim it says,
wait a minute, oh
yeah, אם כסף תלוה את עמי את העני עמך לא תהיה לו
כנושה לא תשימון עליו נשך. im kesef talveh et ami et he'ani
imach lo tihiyeh lo k'nosheh lo tsimun alav neshech. Don't charge interest.
Okay, but when it says that's in משפטים כב כה. Mishpatim chaf-bet
chaf-hey. Okay, but לא תהיה לו כנושה, lo tihiyeh lo k'nosheh, it
ends with don't charge interest and we assume what that means is
that's just a lead-in. How do you act
like a lender? נושה's nosheh a lender, like exert your power? You're
going to exact interest from him. But this actually is a לא
תעשה lo taseh independent of exacting interest. And this is a לא
תעשה lo taseh of, I'll read you in the רמב״ם Rambam and
this is really the most explicit of the power issue. כל הנוגש
את העני והוא יודע שאין לו, kol hanogesh et he'ani v'hu yodeya
she-ein lo, you basically say, Michael, where's my thousand dollars? And I
know he doesn't have the money to pay. But I, so why
am I asking him? You know, basically to exert my power over
him. Okay, ואין לו מה יחזיר לו, v'ein lo mah yachazir lo,
עובר בלא תעשה over b'lo taseh שנאמר shene'emar לא תהיה לו כנושה.
lo tihiyeh lo k'nosheh. Okay? And then the רמב״ם Rambam says אסור,
assur, that's
דאורייתא, d'oraita, לאדם להראות לבעל חובו בזמן שיודע שאין לו, l'adam l'herot
l'ba'al chovo bizman sheyodeya she-ein lo, אפילו לעבור לפניו שלא יפחידו או
יכלימו אף על פי שאינו תובעו. afilu la'avor l'fanav shelo yafchido o
yachlimo af al pi she-eino tove'o. I
can't even walk where I know
Michael... I'm going to the store just so Michael sees me and
remembers that he owes me money. Okay, that is at least a
ד'רבנן d'rabbanan extension of לא תהיה לו כנושה, lo tihyeh lo k'nosheh,
making him feel embarrassed, making him feel my power over him, his
indebtedness to me. So that's why I think that a lot of
these, some of these is to protect the poor person, right, the
רחיים ורכב, reichayim v'rechev, the returning the stuff to the עני, ani,
but there are some that don't have to do with the poor
person. Right? Don't enter his house, don't go ahead and demonstrate your
power over him, which is not limited just about the poor, it
really is about the power dynamic. So those are some of the
מצוות mitzvot or that we are going to be looking at and
I had to start because the גמרא Gemara does not sort of
line them up and place them. So hopefully this will help orient.
One minute I'll take the question but I want to at least
anchor this in a text. So let's at least now start by
reading the
משנה Mishnah on קיי"ג עמוד א'. Kuf Yud Gimmel Amud Aleph. המלווה
חברו, hamalvei chavero, somebody who lends
his friend money, לא ימשכננו אלא בבית דין, lo yimshakneno ela b'veit
din, do not take collateral except through the בית דין Beit Din
because it says don't enter into his house. Well, if I don't
enter into his house, how am I going to get him to
how
am I going to get him to provide? You see him in
the marketplace, you see him...
Ah, so that's a good question. We'll get to that in the
גמרא. Gemara. Okay. Can I force him, exert this power that we've
been talking about in the marketplace, if I don't invade his house?
That's a good question. But the משנה Mishnah says no. The only
legitimate recourse I have obviously is to use בית דין. Beis Din.
ולא יכנס לביתו ליטול משכונו v'lo yikanes l'veito litol mashkono and don't
enter his house to get the משכון. mashkon. This is presumably the
flip side of what we just said, שנאמר בחוץ תעמוד, shene'emar bachutz
ta'amod, stand on the outside. And this is not limited to an
עני. ani. היו לו שני כלים. hayu lo shnei keilim. Now let's
say this now, although not set explicitly in the משנה, Mishnah, which
is why it was important to preface it, is now going to
an עני ani case. We're now moving from this part of the
פסוק pasuk to this second part. ואם איש עני הוא. v'im ish
ani hu. You know, I went through בית דין, Beis Din, I
got your... you only had שני כלים shnei keilim that we could
seize. Okay, and we seize them. Okay, now, and one of them
is basically your day clothes and the other are your night clothes,
for example. So in that case, נוטל אחד ומניח אחד. notel echad
u'maniach echad. I take one and I leave you the other, like
I leave you your day clothes in the day, and as we'll
see, ומחזיר את הכר בלילה ואת המחרשה ביום. umachazir et hakar balaila
v'et hamachresha bayom. You give him back the pillow at night, and
let's say these are the two כלים, keilim, I made them clothes,
but let's say whatever, these are work כלים. keilim. One, I give
you the pillow at night and I take and the...
and the plough in the day.
Now I want to get back to say something about the plough
in a minute. Okay, but this is the idea of you're an
עני, ani, so I have to give you back what you, you
know, presumably, and we generalize this not just to give it back
whatever, at the time you need it. We generalize this, at the
time you need it, I have to give it back to you.
Okay, now we're going to finish the משנה. Mishnah. Okay. ואם מת
אינו
מחזיר ליורשיו. v'im met eino machzir l'yorshav. Now this מצוה mitzvah to
give back to the person only applies to the person
himself. בעבותו, ba'avoto, right. If he dies, then you can hold it
and basically you don't have to give it back on a daily
basis. Either hold it and liquidate it to pay off your loan
or just hold it until you get your loan paid off. רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל
אומר, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer, אף לעצמו אינו מחזיר. af l'atzmo
eino machzir. You don't even have to give it back to the
person himself אלא עד שלשים יום. ela ad shloshim yom. This idea
of every day giving it back to him when he needs it
is only for thirty days. Okay. Now, משלשים יום ולהלן מוכרן בבית
דין. mishloshim yom u'lehalan mocheran b'veis din. After that point, you can
move from your... this is an important question.
Yes, right, thirty days actually holding...
Yes, right. Thanks for clarifying. But one minute. This is an important
question about the stage of holding the collateral to actually, you know,
getting your loan paid off. Okay, so what רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, this מצוה mitzvah of constantly returning it
is when you're at the stage of you still owe me the
money and I'm holding your collateral. But at a certain point you're
entitled to say enough already. It's I need to get my loan
paid. And Michael correctly says, I should have said it earlier, that
this whole idea of you entering the house, when is that happening?
We said it's not at the time of the loan, but also
רש"י Rashi explains it's after the loan was due. Right? You lent
me money and I didn't ask for collateral. I mean, I lent
Michael money, I didn't ask for collateral. So what entitles me during
the, let's say he had three months to pay off. Why would
I think I would have a right to go into his home?
He has three months to pay off. I didn't take... he didn't
give me collateral. I mean, or anyway, how could I get בית
דין Beis Din to collect or take collateral? Right? The time hasn't
come. But now the three months are over and he hasn't paid
me. So now I have the right to do something to either
seize the money or at least take some steps to ensure I'll
get paid. So now I have the right to take collateral שלא
בשעת הלואה shelo b'shat halva'ah because it's already the loan is already
due. I can't enter into the house, I get בית דין Beis
Din to help me. Right, that's this issue. But I still have
a right to take collateral. Okay, good. Now I've got collateral to
help ensure it's going to get paid. At what time are we
going to say enough already? Now I can actually seize the property,
not as collateral, but as payment. So רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says after a month you can now get paid
and you can just sell the property. You don't have to worry
about returning. Okay, now there were questions.
Yes, I wanted to understand though about... Let's say my blanket, whatever
it is, and he's an עני. ani. Like, you know, there's different...
there's עני, ani, like, let's say I have two blankets. You know,
are you allowed to take the other one? Like, you know, there's...
Yes, if you don't need it. I mean, we'll get to all
those פרטים. pratim. I mean, that's why we're learning.
And if I'm rich and I have ten suits, and I don't
want to have the other... but and you took my Armani suit
and now I want to wear that?
I can get that back? No, no. This is only by an
עני. ani.
Right, so I can't get that back. Correct. Okay.
No one has an obligation to give or take collateral, right?
No one has an... well, I could say I'm not going to
lend you money until you give me collateral, and I have a
right to seize collateral if you're in arrears.
Right, so all I'm saying is that there is an interesting issue
about rights that's built into this. Right.
Okay. Are you even going back to my point about obligations? Right.
I mean, right.
Interesting point. Right. The second thing is I get to take your
plow at night. Yeah, that's really helpful. And then in the sunrise,
I'm going to give it back.
So what good does it... how does it help you?
Right. Exactly.
So what it might just do is it might just exert some
subtle pressure and remind... Psychological. Right. I mean, the רמב״ם Rambam says
if you want to hear what the... I mean, the רמב״ם Rambam
is getting it from the גמרא, Gemara, but the רמב״ם Rambam explicitly
addresses this.
Does it give anything other than a psychological...
Right, so here's what the רמב״ם Rambam says. Here's what the רמב״ם
Rambam says, okay? רמב״ם Rambam says the following.
You could have my tablet. Okay. אם כן הוא... Im ken hu...
פרק
ג הלכה ה Perek Gimmel Halacha Hey in the רמב״ם. Rambam. אם
כן הוא שמחזיר לו המשכון בעת שצריך לו ולוקחו מעמו בעת שאינו
צריך לו מה יועיל המשכון? Im ken hu she-machzir lo ha-mashkon b’et
she-tzarich lo u-lokcho m’imo b’et she-eino tzarich lo mah yo’il ha-mashkon? Okay.
כדי... Kedei... what a stupid... כדי שלא ישמט החוב בשביעית. Kedei shelo
yishmat ha-chov bi-shevi’it. First of all, there's something practical. Because I'm holding
on to a משכון, mashkon, it's not... שמיטה shemittah doesn't annul it,
because it's like I already have the property in my possession. ולא
יעשו מטלטלין אצלו בניו. V’lo ye’asu metaltelin etzlo banav. If the guy
dies, then it also somehow ensures that I'll be collected. So those
are some technical things. אלא יפרע מן המשכון שביד הלווה. Ela yipara
min ha-mashkon she-beyad ha-loveh. So those are like one or two technical
things. הא למדת שאין ממשכנין את העני אלא בשביל שיחזירו לו. Ha
lamadta she-ein memashkenin et ha-ani ela bishvil she-yachziru lo. No, then he
goes on. So the רמב״ם Rambam says there are one or two
technical things. But the other thing I would say is that, like
the גמרא Gemara at one point says, זכרון דברים בעלמא. Zichron devarim
be’alma. It makes me remember, it makes it clear that I'm not
מוחל mochel it, it exerts a certain subtle pressure on you. But
yes, there are those questions. Eventually, you will get paid up, okay?
I mean, maybe, you know, that's like רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says after a month, you can now demand to
be paid. Alright, let's take a look. Oh, I wanted to say
one thing about the מחרשה, machresha, okay? So, which is... Tosafos... you
know what, let's not say something about the מחרשה. machresha. We'll get
back to it when we see it in the גמרא Gemara later.
Let's start moving in the גמרא. Gemara. Yes. At thirty days, the
loan is due. So what is he doing before the loan is
due?
Is he giving it back and forth every day? No, before the
loan is due, he's not taking it at all. Now let's say
he took
a משכון mashkon at the time of the loan.
Does this מצוה mitzvah apply?
Or is this מצוה mitzvah only something that was taken after the
loan was in arrears? So that, as I said, somewhat there's a
whole... I have to check again how רמב״ם Rambam פוסק posek about
that. But the פשט pshat of most... most assume that all of
these things is... I mean this, okay? Right? There's all these interesting...
לא יחבול בגד אלמנה, Lo yachavol beged almanah, לא יחבול רחיים ורכב.
lo yachavol rechayim va-rechev. Would that even apply at the time of
the loan, right? Or is that only after the loan? That's the
debate of רמב״ם Rambam and ראב״ד. Ra’avad. But this, yeah, but this...
I think I have to... I have to double check. I'm pretty
sure רמב״ם Rambam says the same thing here as he does by
בגד אלמנה. beged almanah. But this, פשט pshat of this is all
after the loan. It's all about the exertion of power, and he
hasn't paid up, okay? So that's sort of the case we're talking
about, not something that was made at the time of the loan.
Let's start seeing the גמרא. Gemara. Alright. אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. שליח
בית דין מנתח נתוחי. Shliach Beit Din menateach nituchei. A שליח בית
דין Shliach Beit Din can do operations. No, that's contemporary. A שליח
בית דין Shliach Beit Din can seize something out, like grab something
from somebody out in the public domain. Okay, grab something off somebody's
back in, yes. אבל ממשכני לא. Aval memashkeni lo. He cannot... משכון
mashkon means enter into the house to take the collateral. Okay, so
this is the question. Can you, because I was mentioning power, and
actually the phrase רמב״ם Rambam uses is when he talks about the
פסוק pasuk of לא תבוא אל ביתו Lo tavo el beito is
למשכנו בזרוע, lemashkeno bizroa, to exert your power to take it. So
there's one thing about entering into the house. What about exerting the
power outside of the house? So שמואל Shmuel says even that is
limited to בית דין. Beit Din. בית דין, Beit Din, even בית
דין Beit Din cannot go into your house. The most I can
do in this situation is involve בית דין Beit Din and seize
it outside of your house. Isn't that הפקר בית דין הפקר? Hefker
Beit Din Hefker? No, not הפקר. hefker. I'm using בית דין Beit
Din to collect collateral. But I'm saying even בית דין Beit Din
is limited not to enter into your house. So let's keep... let's
read a little. אבל ממשכני לא. Aval memashkeni lo. והתנן: Ve-hatnan: המלווה
את חבירו לא ימשכננו אלא בבית דין. Ha-malveh et chaveiro lo yemashkenenu
ela be-Beit Din. That if you lent it you cannot be משכון
mashkon and the word משכון mashkon seems to be entering into the
house to take the משכון mashkon except with בית דין. Beit Din.
מכלל דבבית דין ממשכנין. Miklal d'be-veis din memashkenin. It sounds like through
בית דין Beis Din I can enter into your home. אמר ליה
שמואל, Amar lei Shmuel, so or אמר לך שמואל, Amar lach Shmuel,
שמואל Shmuel would say to you, אימא, eima, no, here's how you
should read the משנה. mishna. לא ינתחנהו אלא בבית דין. Lo yenatchenu
ela be-veis din. If you're coming to collect collateral, you cannot seize
it without בית דין. Beis Din. But even with בית דין, Beis
Din, you can only seize it in the street. You can't enter
into the person's house. Okay? הכי נמי מסתברא. Hachi nami mistabra. The
גמרא Gemara says, you know what, that actually is a good read
of the משנה. mishna. דקתני סיפא, Dekatani seifa, לא יכנס לביתו ליטול
משכונו. Lo yikanes leveito litol mashkono. At the end of the משנה,
mishna, right after saying don't take collateral, it says don't enter into
his house. So we already said don't take collateral. Why do you
have to now say don't enter into his house? מני, Mani, who
are we talking about? אילימא בעל חוב, Ilima baal chov, if it's
the creditor, מרישא שמע מינה. Me-reisha shma mina. You already said in
the first line of the משנה, mishna, don't take collateral from the
guy. אלא לאו שליח בית דין. Ela lav shaliach beis din. It
must mean nobody can enter into that house. You the debtor, you
can't force seize collateral anywhere, and nobody, even בית דין Beis Din
can't enter into the house. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says no,
אי משום הא לא איריא. Ei mishum ha lo irya. If that
was your whole proof, that's you can't prove it textually. הכי קאמר.
Hachi ka'amar. Here's how I could read the משנה. mishna. המלווה את
חבירו לא ימשכננו אלא בבית דין. Hamalveh es chaveiro lo yemashkenenu ela
be-veis din. When you lend your money, don't enter into the house
except through don't don't take a משכון, mashkon, meaning enter the house
except with בית דין. Beis Din. מכלל דבבית דין ממשכנין. Miklal d'be-veis
din memashkenin. And I would say that with בית דין Beis Din
you can enter into the house. ובעל חוב, U-baal chov, but but
for you the actual creditor, אפילו מבחוץ נמי לא. afilu mibachutz nami
lo. You with בית דין Beis Din you can even enter into
the house. But you the creditor, not only can you not enter
into the house, you can never take any collateral, even in the
street. Why? From having the word גזירה. gezeira. גזירה שלא יכנס לביתו
ליטול משכונו. Gezeira shelo yikanes leveito litol mashkono. So it shouldn't lead
to you entering into the house. So meaning that the משנה mishna
could be read that when it says המלווה את חבירו לא ימשכננו
אלא בבית דין, Hamalveh es chaveiro lo yemashkenenu ela be-veis din, you
don't enter into the house except בית דין Beis Din does. בית
דין Beis Din enters into the house. And then it says ולא
יכנס לביתו ליטול משכונו. Velo yikanes leveito litol mashkono. It's saying but
as far as you're concerned, it's a little hard to read, don't
do anything even seize it in public because it can lead to
you entering into the house. Like a type of a גזירה. gezeira.
Rambam I should again repeat that it's from the Rambam it's not
clear that this idea of seizing somebody's property even in public is
only a גזירה. gezeira. Rambam actually frames the איסור, issur, although the
Torah says לא יבוא אל ביתו, Lo yavo el beito, as to
לא ימשכננו בזרועו. Lo yemashkenenu bizroa'o. So don't so use force to
take, you know don't exert your power. Anyway, bottom line is here's
the story. Everybody agrees that the creditor cannot enter into the house,
which is clear in the פסוקים. pesukim. And everybody also agrees, which
is not clear in the פסוקים, pesukim, that the creditor cannot forcefully
seize the property even in the street. You can go up to
the guy maybe and ask him, "Look buddy, you're, you know, 20
days in arrears, can you please give me something for collateral?" Okay,
but the but you can't forcefully seize it. So for the creditor,
nothing. The question is בית דין. Beis Din. Can בית דין Beis
Din enter the house or can even even בית דין Beis Din
is limited to the street. And see I would say, going back
to my little מחלוקת machlokes with מנחם אלון, Menachem Elon, you know
that this issue, I think, is a question about do we are
we seeing here a fundamental right that, you know, my sort of
what we would call a right of privacy or a right to
not have my, you know, domain invaded? Here's a question: does that
apply even to בית דין, Beis Din, right? Or is it only
if it only applies to the creditor, then I would say and
I think the פשט pshat is that it's about that power relationship.
But if even the court, right, that's like the right against, you
know, search and seizure without a warrant. If even the court cannot
enter into somebody's home when they have a legal basis for doing
so, right, so then that does seem to point to a more
general issue and not just the power dynamics of the creditor and
the borrower. So this is the question of the גמרא. Gemara. Is
the court itself, you know, prohibited from entering in the home? Yes.
See, this is what I was trying to understand. This is what
I was trying to get to like early on in history, for
instance, like let's say it wasn't a loan. Let's say you're a
מזיק. mazik. Right. And you owe somebody and then בית דין Beis
Din says, "All right, you gotta pay, you haven't paid." Can they
go into your house? Right. And take your assets? Right, so that
is a very good question. What would be about if the court
has a right to do this, but not in the context of
a loan, like in seizing property? Like they could seize your real
estate, but how about if they want to check your house to
see what types of things you're hiding away, cash you're hiding under
your mattress? Right, are they entitled to do that? So that's a
very good question. I'll get to I mean I don't have the
full answer for you, but I'll get back to that in a
little bit. Okay, so let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, okay, מתיב רב יוסף. Masiv Rav Yosef.
So now we're going to spend most of the hour trying to
figure out whether בית דין Beis Din is allowed to enter into
the home or not to collect the loan. מתיב רב יוסף. Masiv
Rav Yosef. רב יוסף Rav Yosef asked, לא יחבול ריחיים ורכב. Lo
yachavol reichayim varachev. Do not take a ריחיים ורכב, reichayim varachev, and
that's presumably from anybody. It doesn't mention an עני, ani, right? And
as the Rambam framed it, דברים שעושים בהם אוכל נפש. devarim she-osim
bahem ochel nefesh. Is that one implement that goes together? No, I
think it's two. The רכב rechev is like a separate... no, I
think... I think it's different parts of the millstone. Two parts of
the same? Two parts, yeah. I believe so, yeah. הדברים אחרים חבול
*Ha'devarim acheirim chavol*, other things you can take as collateral. And we
are assuming, and רש"י Rashi *Rashi* makes this point, the same way
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumed the word ממשכנין *memashkenin* means enter the
home, we're assuming the word חובל *chovel* means enter the home to
take collateral. Why? Because as רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says, לא יחבול רחיים
ורכב *lo yachavol rechayim varachev*. Where else would you get the רחיים
ורכב *rechayim varachev* without entering into the guy's home? So the very
word חובל *chovel* and ממשכנין *memashkenin*, the presumption is it means enter
the home in order to seize. That's the assumption we're making. Okay,
so here it says you can't take those things. You can't enter
the home to seize those things. הדברים אחרים, השאר... לא I'm sorry,
הדברים אחרים חבול *ha'devarim acheirim chavol*, other things you can enter into
the home to seize. Okay. Similarly, לא תחבול בגד אלמנה *lo tachavol
beged almanah*. Don't take a garment of an אלמנה *almanah*, which really
means don't take anything from an אלמנה *almanah* as collateral. השאר תחבול
*ha'shear tachavol*, property of others you can enter into the home. So
who are we entering into the home here? מני *Mani*, who are
we talking about? אי נימא בבעל חוב *ei neima be'baal chov*, if
it's the actual creditor, הכתיב לא תבא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו *haksiv
lo tavo el beito la'avot avoto*. No, you can never enter the
home. אלא לאו שליח בית דין *ela lav sheliach beis din*. You
can see implicitly from the פסוקים psukim *psukim* that there are times
when the home can be entered and that proves that at least
בית דין *beis din* can enter the home. So תרגמה רב פפא
בריה דרב נחמן קמיה דרב יוסף *Targemah Rav Papa breih de-Rav Nachman
kamei de-Rav Yosef*, איכא דאמרי רב פפא בריה דרב יוסף קמיה דרב
יוסף *ika d'amri Rav Papa breih de-Rav Yosef kamei de-Rav Yosef*. Okay,
one רב פפא *Rav Papa* who said to רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*.
לעולם בבעל חוב *Le'olam be'baal chov*. Nope, we are talking about the
בעל חוב baal chov, *baal chov*. So I don't get it. Why
do you have to say don't enter the home to take a
בגד אלמנה *beged almanah*, רחיים ורכב *rechayim varachev*? You can never enter
the home anyway. לעבור עליו בשני לאוין *la'avor alav bi'shnei lavin*. No,
in order to give you two transgressions, but it doesn't imply that
somebody else is ever permitted. Okay. Yes, anybody who would enter the
home would
transgress anyway, and now it says and not only that, there's another
transgression if it's a בגד אלמנה *beged almanah* or if it's a
רחיים ורכב *rechayim varachev*. Okay. But on the face of it, it
was a very good proof, right? That it seems like there are
times when it is permissible, at least for בית דין *beis din*
to enter the home. תא שמע Tashma, *Ta shema*, come and hear.
ממאי דמשמע דבידו שנאמר בחוץ תעמוד *mimai d'mashma d'be-yado shene'emar bachutz ta'amod*?
אני יודע שהאיש אשר אתה נושה בו יוציא *ani yodeia she'ha'ish asher
atah nosheh bo yotzi*. Obviously, I know the end of the פסוק
pasuk *pasuk*. If you have to wait outside, of course the guy
has to bring it out, because you can't go in. Okay. אלא
מה תלמוד לומר והאיש *ela mah talmud lomar ve'ha'ish*? So what's the
והאיש *ve'ha'ish* that part of the פסוק *pasuk* telling me? That the
person will bring it out. Now if you ask me at a
פשט *peshat* level what that פסוק *pasuk* is telling me is you
don't have to sacrifice your rights. You're still entitled to a משכון
mashkon, *mashkon*, but here's how it has to play out. You stand
outside and the guy will bring it. Don't think that just because
you can't enter the home you have to forfeit your right to
the משכון mashkon? *mashkon*. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying that's
פשט *peshat*. If it says בחוץ תעמוד *bachutz ta'amod*, it doesn't say
don't do it, it says בחוץ תעמוד *bachutz ta'amod*. So what are
you waiting outside for? Obviously, he's going to bring it to you.
So why does it have to say that he's going to bring
it to you? והאיש *Ve'ha'ish*? לרבות שליח בית דין *le'rabos sheliach beis
din*. To tell you that including the case of the שליח בית
דין *sheliach beis din*. So what does that mean? So it reads
the פסוק *pasuk*, oh, I don't have it. I didn't put it
up there. לא תבא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו והאיש אשר אתה נושה
בו יוציא אליך את העבוט החוצה *lo tavo el beito la'avot avoto
ve'ha'ish asher atah nosheh bo yotzi elecha es ha'avot hachutzah*. It means
that והאיש *ve'ha'ish*, the person, not the person, two people in the
פסוק *pasuk*. Okay. לא תבא אל ביתו לעבוט עבוטו והאיש אשר אתה
נושה בו יוציא אליך את העבוט החוצה *lo tavo el beito
la'avot avoto ve'ha'ish asher atah nosheh bo yotzi elecha es ha'avot hachutzah*.
Sounds like it's one person, the לוה *loveh* will bring it out.
But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* reads it: you don't
go in, but two people can bring it out to you.
Who are the two people who can bring it out to you?
The man, you know, what it says the man, right? The man,
the authority, or אשר אתה נושה בו *asher atah nosheh bo*. One
of those two people will bring it out to you. Either the
guy who you've lent the money to, or the man, the שליח
בית דין *sheliach beis din* will bring it out to you. Okay.
So that's how we're reading it to show a שליח בית דין
*sheliach beis din* is allowed to enter in. So the whole issue
of שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* is as you've been saying
the issue of the parameters of power. Right, but it's a different
power. This is the power of governmental authority, not the interpersonal power
of the מלוה *malveh* and לוה *loveh*. But it's still a power
issue, right, where parameters are circumscribed and where they're not. Exactly. And
going back to that question, even if the שליח בית דין *sheliach
beis din* is prohibited to enter the home, right, it doesn't mean
that in another that a סתם Stam *stam* my next-door neighbor has
the same prohibition. Right, because the power issue is different, or if
it's not a מלוה *malveh* context, the power issues are different. So
you know, there's all these questions to ask of the parameters. Do
you make anything of the fact that the verb יחבול *yachavol* here,
which means to enter to seize, is the verb that they use
to do that? That's an interesting point. Yeah. לא תחבול רחיים ורכב
*lo tachavol rechayim varachev* and לא תחבול בגד אלמנה *lo tachavol beged
almanah*. Those two things which are about sort of disadvantaged people. Right,
that's a very good point. Yep. Okay. אלא מה תלמוד לומר והאיש
לרבות שליח בית דין *ela mah talmud lomar ve'ha'ish le'rabos sheliach beis
din*. מאי לאו שליח בית דין כלוה *mai lav sheliach beis din
ke'loveh*? Just like the לוה *loveh* brings out the money, the שליח...
שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* brings out the money. So the
גמרא Gemara *gemara* says לא *lo* שליח בית דין כמלווה *sheliach beis
din kemalveh*. No, here's how you read it. Not two people bring
out the money. לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט עבותו *lo tavo el
beiso la'avot avoso* והאיש *veha'ish*. Neither you nor the man, I love
it, the man, right? Anyway, neither you nor the שליח בית דין
*sheliach beis din* can go into the home. The only person who
can go who can bring it out to you is the לווה
*loveh*. Okay, so which part, we're reading the word איש *ish* as
extra? And the question is which part of the פסוק *pasuk* are
we reading them? He together with you cannot enter into the home?
That's to say, or do we read, no, you can't, but he
together with the לווה *loveh* can bring out the עבות *avot*. Two
ways of reading it. Okay, תא שמע *ta shema*, come and hear.
אם חבל תחבל שלמת רעך *im chavo tachvol salmas re'echa*, if you
go, you know, go ahead and take his collateral. עד בוא השמש
תשיבנו לו Lo, *ad bo hashemesh teshiveno lo*, return it before the
sun goes down. Okay, but so who's taking this collateral? How is
this collateral seized? Okay, so the ברייתא Baraita *braisa* says, בשליח בית
דין הכתוב מדבר *besheliach beis din hakasuv medaber*. You use the שליח
בית דין *sheliach beis din* to take the collateral and now you're
going to have to, you know, return it if he's a poor
person on a regular basis. Okay, now, או אינו אלא בבעל חוב
*o eino ela beba'al chov*, maybe it's talking about maybe you the
creditor seize this collateral that you're now going to return on a
regular basis. הרי הוא אומר *harei hu omer* לא תבוא אל ביתו
לעבוט עבותו *lo tavo el beiso la'avot avoso*, הרי בבעל חוב אמור
*harei beba'al chov amur*. No, obviously you didn't seize the collateral because
you weren't allowed to go into the home. Now of course why
didn't it just say that he brought it out to you? Like
I don't know why it has to be you. But again, it's
this word of חבול *chavol*, אם חבל תחבל *im chavo tachvol* means
entering into the home, right? That's the key of the question. So
who has entered into the home to get this collateral that now
is being returned on a regular basis? It can't be the בעל
חוב baal chov, *ba'al chov*, he's not allowed to enter into the
home. Yeah, yeah, maybe from חבלה *chavalah*. Right. או לחבול *o lachvol*
maybe based... וזה בלווה *veze beloveh*. וזה *veze*. אה *ah*. That could
be right because it says מה זה חבלה *mah zeh chavalah*. Well,
that's what Rabbi Dov said, that maybe it has the echo of
injury. Right, right, right. So anyway, so here it has the Torah's
case of returning the collateral is a case that first was seized
by entering into the home, that's how חבול *chavol* is being read.
Well, who entered into the home? Okay, לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט
עבותו *lo tavo el beiso la'avot avoso*, הרי בבעל חוב אמור *harei
beba'al chov amur*. הא מה אני מקיים אם חבל תחבל *ha mah
ani mekayem im chavo tachvol*, so who, how did you enter the
home to take the collateral? שלמת רעך בשליח בית דין הכתוב מדבר
*salmas re'echa besheliach beis din hakasuv medaber*. So here's an explicit ברייתא
Baraita? *braisa* that says that yes, a שליח בית דין *sheliach beis
din* could enter into the home. Okay, and there you and that's
how you got that collateral. So גמרא Gemara *gemara* says fine, תנאי
היא *tannai hi*, it's a debate of תנאים Tannaim *tannaim* whether a
שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* can enter into the home. דתניא
*detanya*, we taught in a ברייתא Baraita. *braisa*. שליח בית דין שבא
למשכנו *sheliach beis din sheba lemaskeno*, if the שליח בית דין *sheliach
beis din* came to seize the
collateral, לא יכנס לביתו *lo yikanes leveiso* למשכנו *lemaskeno*. Here we have
an explicit ברייתא Baraita. *braisa*. One ברייתא braita. *braisa* explicitly said שליח
בית דין *sheliach beis din* is entitled, and
this ברייתא *braisa* says, no, a שליח בית דין
*sheliach beis din* is prohibited, cannot
enter to the home למשכנו *lemaskeno*.
אלא עומד מבחוץ *ela omed mibachutz*, and even the שליח בית דין
*sheliach beis din* has to stand outside, והלה מוציא לו את המשכון
*vehala motzi lo es hamashkon*, and the other guy brings it out.
שנאמר בחוץ תעמד והאיש *shene'emar bachutz ta'amod veha'ish*. So reading והאיש *veha'ish*
with this, right? לא תבוא אל ביתו לעבוט עבותו בחוץ תעמד והאיש
*lo tavo el beiso la'avot avoso bachutz ta'amod veha'ish*, okay. I thought
I forgot that part of the פסוק *pasuk*. בחוץ תעמד *bachutz ta'amod*,
you have to stand, והאיש *veha'ish*, and the man has to stand.
Even the שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* has to wait outside.
So one ברייתא *braisa* said שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* can
enter, one says the שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* cannot enter.
Okay, ותניא אידך *vesanya idach*, we taught another ברייתא *braisa*. בעל חוב
baal chov שבא למשכנו *ba'al chov sheba lemaskeno*, now if the creditor
is coming to take collateral, לא יכנס לביתו למשכנו *lo yikanes leveiso
lemaskeno*, don't go into the home, אלא עומד בחוץ והלה נכנס ומוציא
לו משכונו *ela omed bachutz vehala nichnas umotzi lo mashkono*, stand outside
and the הלה *hala* now, and at this stage presumably the הלה
*hala* means that's the לווה *loveh*, נכנס ומוציא לו משכונו *nichnas umotzi
lo mashkono*, the לווה *loveh* goes and brings you out the collateral.
שנאמר בחוץ תעמד *shene'emar bachutz ta'amod*. ושליח בית דין שבא למשכנו *vesheliach
beis din sheba lemaskeno*, but if you've got if you've got a
שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din*, הרי זה נכנס לביתו וממשכנו *harei
zeh nichnas leveiso umemaskeno*, he can go in. So basically this whole
question is a debate of תנאים *tannaim*. Does a שליח בית דין
*sheliach beis din* have a right to enter in? And from a
דרשה *drasha* point do you put the והאיש *veha'ish*, which is being
read as שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din*, in the first half
of the פסוק *pasuk* or the second half of the פסוק *pasuk*?
Let's just finish the top of the עמוד Amud *amud* תא שמע
*ta shema*. Let's finish this ברייתא *braisa*. Okay, ולא ימשכננו דברים שעושים
בהם אוכל נפש *velo yemashkenenu devarim she'osim bahem ochel nefesh*. Even when
שליח בית דין *sheliach beis din* is going in, you cannot take
דברים שעושים בהם אוכל נפש *devarim she'osim bahem ochel nefesh*, that's this
prohibition, even presumably not limited to an עני *ani*. Okay, אוכל נפש
*ochel nefesh*. ונותן *venosen* now, what what do you have to leave
behind? You're not going to take stuff that's made for providing food.
Okay, you entered into the home, you're taking collateral, you're not going
to leave stuff take stuff that's for providing food. If it's stuff
that he needs you're going to return it on a regular basis.
Okay, but what do you take in terms of what do you
have to leave him with? Right, let's say, you know, it's not
like, you know, can you go ahead and seize go to his
closet and empty out his closet and take all of his clothes
or whatever, you know, and can you go ahead and take all
of his furniture, you know, and you know. hold on to that
like, I mean, furniture's a good example, right? Is furniture, you know,
when the גמרא Gemara. says like, what are these, you know, there's
two questions, like what are the things you have to. hold on
to that like, I mean, furniture's a good example, right? Is furniture,
you know, when the גמרא Gemara, says like, what are these, you
know, there's two questions, like what are the things you have to
return, but also what are the things that you have to leave
behind and not seize in the first place. So here the ברייתא
says, let's just read it: ונותן לו, V'noten lo, but you have
to leave behind, like not even take, not even take and then
return. You have to leave behind when you're seizing this collateral, מיטה
ומיטה ומצע, Mita umita umatza, a bed and a bed and a
cushion, לעשיר, La'ashir, for a rich person. So two beds, we'll see
what the two beds are for. מיטה ומיטה ומפץ, Mita umita umapatz,
and two beds and a מפץ, mapatz, which is a more like
a thinner type of a, like a mat, okay, because rich poor
people don't have nice thick cushions, לעני, Le'ani, for a poor person.
לו, right, so we could be talking about a rich person, but
he's still not paying his debts, and you're going to go into
his home and take all his stuff. Leave behind two beds and
a mattress, okay, and only for him, אבל לא לאשה ולא לבנים
ולבנות. Aval lo l'isha v'lo l'banim v'livnot. You don't have any responsibility
to leave behind anything for his family. Like that's his problem, okay,
which sounds very harsh, alright? But you know, your relationship is with
him. He's got responsibilities to his family, that's his issue. You just
have to leave him with some basic stuff for himself. כדרך שמסדרים
בבעל חוב. Kederech shemesadrin b'baal chov. So I'll pause here for a
second. Dov, you had a question about something earlier. Is it פשוט?
pashut? That תא שמע, that happened that the עמוד that begins this
is a ברייתא? Yes. I mean, sometimes the גמרא Gemara doesn't tell
you, you know, but yes, it's a ברייתא. Okay, so. Yeah, what
was the first thing that he's left behind? That's what we're about
to get to. Okay, and that's the next line of the ברייתא.
כדרך שמסדרים בבעל חוב כך מסדרים בערכין. Kederech shemesadrin b'baal chov kach
mesadrin b'erchin. The same way you arrange things for the בעל חוב,
Ba'al chov. meaning even when you're seizing property for, now you know,
here we're assuming it means for a משכון, mashkon. although there's an
interesting question about a similar consideration when you're actually coming to get
your loan paid. What do you have to leave the guy when
you're actually, right, when you're getting your loan paid? Are we talking
about the payment of the loan or the משכון? mashkon, But anyway,
מסדרים mesadrin means you make arrangements, like you don't leave the guy
totally with nothing, okay? The same way you do that for a
בעל חוב, baal hov. you do it for ערכין. erchin. What's the
case with ערכין? erchin? ערכין Erchin is I say ערך פלוני עלי,
erech ploni alay, right, people know at the end of ויקרא, Vayikra,
right, if I say the value of somebody is on me, the
תורה Torah says based on the age and the sex, there's a
certain amount, 50 שקל, shekel, 30 שקל, shekel, etc. Then the תורה
Torah says ואם מך הוא מערכך, V'im mach hu me'erkecha, if I
don't have the money to pay what I just vowed to the
בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, והעמידו לפני הכהן, v'he'emido lifnei hakohen, you know,
על פי אשר תשיג יד הנודר יערכנו הכהן. al pi asher tasig
yad hanoder ya'archenu hakohen. The כהן kohen basically, it's sort of like
applying for, you know, financial aid for your kids' day school, right?
They look into your finances, they see what you can afford, על
פי אשר תשיג יד הנודר יערכנו הכהן. al pi asher tasig yad
hanoder ya'archenu hakohen. The כהן kohen assesses, you know, what exactly that
you can afford, oh sorry, the כהן kohen assesses what it is
that you can afford. And then he says, okay, looking at all
your finances I see you owed 30 שקל shekel but really you
can only afford 15 שקל. shekel. And therefore the הלכה halacha is,
is that you pay 15 שקל shekel and then you're done, okay?
It's not like you owe the rest. That's the חידוש chiddush of
the פסוק by ערכין, erchin, על פי אשר תשיג יד הנודר. al
pi asher tasig yad hanoder. That if you can't afford it, we
redetermine how much you owe based on what you can afford. Now
what does it mean what you can afford? You know, when people
apply for like financial aid from schools, right, they say sort of
like, please list any vacations you take, camps you send your kids
to. Like I'm serious, you know, what is the question about how
much money I have, you know, how much you assume is the
basic amount I need to live off of before you then say
how much can I afford? So that's the phrase of מסדרים בערכין.
mesadrin b'erchin. Oh, for God's sake, excuse me a second. Hello? Sweetie,
I'm in the middle of a שיעור. shiur. I'll call you back
in 10 minutes, okay? Oh, okay. Well, I might be doing something.
Alright, then we'll do it later, okay? Okay, bye. Sorry. Okay, so
wait, I thought, oh, okay, anyway, so where were we? Okay, so
that's called מסדרים בערכין, mesadrin b'erchin, where we assess how much you
can afford. That redetermines how much you owe the בית המקדש Beit
Hamikdash in a specific case of ערך. erech. It's not all times
you owe money to the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, specifically by ערכין.
erchin. But it starts by us first determining what are your basic
needs. Okay, so the same way by the בעל חוב we allow
you your basic needs and we seize the rest, either for payment
or for collateral, not exactly clear. Similarly by ערכין erchin we determine
your basic needs and we use the rest to determine what you
can afford to pay for the ערך erech that you vowed. Okay,
so that's what it says. So now the גמרא Gemara immediately challenges
this. Okay, let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara says כלפי לייא,
klapi laya, like is this going in the opposite direction? עיקר סידור
בערכין כתיב. Ikar sidur b'erchin ketiv.
And this answers your question, right, the whole way we. We know
this idea that you determine a person's basic needs and then you
look at the rest is from the פסוקים by ערכין. Erchin. That's
where the תורה Torah says כי תשיג יד הנודר יאריכנו הכהן, Ki
tasig yad hanoder yaarichenu hacohen, that
there's an assessment process to determine what can you afford, and we
understand that part of the assessment process is by first giving, like
assuming that you have the right to, you know, to some, to
take care of your basic needs. So that is the source for
the idea that we first give you that. Now this happens right
now on bankruptcy court, right? I mean the tragedy is or the
irony is that somebody could say, well you know you have a
right to domicile. My domicile happens to be at 100,000 square foot
mansion, you know, that you can't seize from me, that I have
to, you know, what exactly is that? But that's so, so we
get that from ערכין Erchin and therefore we apply it to the
case of בעל חוב. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אלא אימא,
Ela eima, fine,
that's how you should read it. כדרך שמסדרין בערכין כך מסדרין בבעל
חוב. K'derech shemesadrin b'erchin kach mesadrin b'baal chov. The same way we
see in the תורה Torah that when a person makes this ערך
erech vow, we determine what he can afford and we first set
aside some basic stuff for his basic needs, the same is true
here. Now again what remains somewhat vague is: do we mean when
the loan is coming to be paid off, or do we mean
when you're coming to take the collateral for the loan? It seems
like the latter. Okay, but it's a little vague. Let's keep on
going in the גמרא. Gemara So now we're going to unpack this
ברייתא. אמר מר, Amar mar, נותן מטה ומטה. noten mita umita. So
when we leave him alone, we leave him his basic needs, and
just for him, not his family, what his basic needs are: two
beds ומצע לעשיר umatzah l'ashir and a nice mattress for an עשיר,
ashir, מטה ומטה ומפץ לעני mita umita umapatz l'ani and two beds
and a mat for a poor person. So למאן, L'man, who's the
other bed for? Says the גמרא, Gemara אילימא לאשתו ובניו ולבנותיו? ilayma
l'ishto u'banav u'livnotav? If it's for his wife and kids, אלא האמרת
לו אבל לא לאשתו לבניו ולבנותיו. ela ha'amart lo aval lo l'ishto
l'banav u'livnotav. We only leave over himself for his own use, then
it's his responsibility to provide for his wife and kids, not ours.
אלא אידי ואידי לדידיה. Ela idi v'idi l'didei. No, he needs two
beds. Why do you need two? תרתי למה לי? Tartei lama li?
Why do you need two? חדא דאכיל עלה, chada d'achil alah, one
that you eat on off of, meaning it's not a bed, it's
essentially a table, right? You know, it's essentially like a long, you
know, if you think about like a divan or something, you know
what I mean? That's what those are called, right? You know what
I'm talking about here? Anyway, so let, no, they're these like, you
know, if you think about the Roman model, right, they reclined on
these beds, and so sometimes a מטה mita is, the גמרא Gemara
says מטה, mita, but it's almost like a coffee table. Right, it's
a long flat thing you could put a mattress on it and
sleep on it or you could, as you're reclining on your bed
or you know, you could be eating off of this and having
it as a type of a table. So one to eat off
of, חדא דאכיל עלה, chada d'achil alah, וחדא דזגיל עלה, v'chada d'zagil
alah, and one that you recline on. Now the question is: that
made sense if you're in Roman times that you're reclining while you're
eating, but in Babylonian times you don't recline while you eat. So
why do you need two? You know, you'll sit down by your
table, you know, and eat off of your bed and then when
it's time to go to sleep you'll clear off, you know, you'll
clear off the table slash bed and turn it into a bed.
Still, why do you need two? Okay, you don't recline in Babylonian
times, you're not reclining and eating at the same time. Wait, let's
just see the גמרא's Gemara answer. Chairs just on the floor, yeah,
like in anyway, I don't know the exact but anyway, in Roman
times we would understand that you need to recline and eat at
the same time, but the גמרא doesn't still get it. So now
it's going to explain why you need two. So the גמרא says
כשמואל, K'Shmuel, like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, as שמואל Shmuel
says, כל מילי ידענא אסיותייהו, kol milei yadana asiyuta'ihu, I know the
cure of any malady לבר מהני תלת l'bar mehani tlat except for
somebody who does one of these three things: מאן דאכיל אהינא מרירא
אליבא ריקנא, man d'achil ahina merira aliba reikana, somebody who eats a
bitter date on an empty heart, meaning on an empty stomach, okay,
ומן דאסר מיתנא דכיתנא רטיבא אחריציה, u'man d'asar mitna d'chitna retiva acharitzai,
somebody who binds a wet rope of flax, a wet flax rope
on his loins, so ties it on, you know, on himself, so
that creates some malady. And the third one is ומן דאכיל נהמא
ולא מסגי ארבע גרמידי, u'man d'achil nahama v'lo masgi arba garmidei, somebody
who eats bread and
doesn't walk four אמות amot
before going down to sleep.
Exercise a little, whatever, before you go, don't eat
and go right to sleep. So therefore, the way רש"י says it
is, here's what would happen. If you only left me one bed,
I'd eat off of the bed and then I'd clear off the
table and I'd go to sleep and I wouldn't walk my ארבע
אמות. arba amot. So because you're giving me two beds, one bed
is out in the living room and one bed is in the
bedroom and one bed's in the dining room and one bed's in
the bedroom, and therefore I will walk from the dining room to
the bedroom. Exactly, exactly. I went to the gym last night, it
was really great. Exactly, exactly. When I once worked with a trainer,
he said, so what exercise do you do today? I said, well,
I walked to the bus, you know, so anyway, right, okay, anyway,
so alright, so תני תנא קמיה דרבי. Tani tana kamei d'Rabbi. תני
תנא קמיה דרב נחמן. Tani tana kmei d'Rav Nachman. Now we're going
to turn our focus to this issue of מסדרין לבעל חוב. mesadrin
l'baal hov. תני תנא קמיה דרב נחמן: Tani tana kmei d'Rav Nachman:
כדרך שמסדרין בערכין כך מסדרין בבעל חוב. Kederech shemesadrin b'archin, kach mesadrin
b'baal hov. Now we have it taught the right way. The same
way we know from ערכין archin you arrange things and you leave
them what he needs, the same thing you do by the בעל
חוב. Now I've been by the way interpreting the word of מסדרין
mesadrin as like to arrange it, like make sure you provided arrangements
for. Rashi also says it might come from the word שריד. sarid.
שריד ופליט Sarid u'falit like a remnant, you give him a remnant.
Okay, anyway, so the Gemara says now, אמר ליה: Amar lei: השתא
זבוני מזבנינן ליה, סידורי מסדרינן ליה? Hashta zevunei mezavninan lei, sidurei mesadrinan
lei? He says, I don't get it, because he understands that we're
talking about when it comes time for payment, not time for משכון.
mashkon. And he says, when it comes time to payment, remember what
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel said? After a month
of holding on to the משכון, mashkon you can liquidate the משכון.
mashkon Right? Everybody remember that from the Mishnah? And what משכון mashkon?
were we talking about, by the way? We were talking about the
משכון that you return on a daily basis. Right? You're returning, returning,
returning, because he's a poor person, he only has like a pillow.
One example was the pillow. You return him the pillow every night.
And רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says very nice,
but after a month, you can go ahead and sell that pillow
to get your loan paid off. Okay? So now he's saying, I
don't get it, what do you mean? Because he understands this idea
of מסדרין mesadrin when it's time to pay the loan. What do
you mean when it's time to pay the loan you leave him
these things? According to רבן שמעון בן גמליאל, Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel,
you're selling his basic necessities when the month is up in order
to get paid. So we're not leaving him anything. And do you
understand the question? The Mishnah was dealing with a case that you
took some basic necessities from a poor person, a pillow, and you
were returning it every night, it was his only pillow. And רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says, when the month is
up and the time comes to get paid, you sell the pillow.
So of course you're not מסדרין, mesadrin, you're not leaving him stuff
over when you're coming to get your loan paid off. No, but
if he understood that the מסדרין mesadrin meant it's now the loan
is being paid and you have to leave stuff behind. Now you
could, right, that's what I said, it's unclear. Is מסדרין mesadrin at
the time of payment or at the time of משכון? But this
question assumes that even at the time of payment, you have to
leave him behind and he says, I don't hear that in רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. From רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel it sounds like at the time of payment
you liquidate everything. Yes, but it sounds like pillow is not the
two beds and a mattress. So maybe you could make a distinction,
but he sort of thinks like it's, you know, like it would
be included in the two beds and the mattress. You could try
to cut, you know, make that distinction. Let's see what the answer
is. Okay. So he says, אמר ליה: Amar lei: השתא זבוני מזבנינן
ליה, hashta zevunei mezavninan lei, if we're going to sell this stuff
and liquidate it, סידורי מסדרינן ליה? sidurei mesadrinan lei? He says, I
don't get it, make up your mind. So the Gemara says, ומי
מזבנינן ליה? U'mi mezavninan lei? Where do you ever hear that we
sell it? והא תני מהדר כסות לילה בלילה וכסות יום ביום. Veha
tani mahader ksut laila balaila u'ksut yom bayom. So maybe we're going
like the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma never
says that you can sell the pillow, right? So maybe you can't
sell it ever. The other stuff you can sell, not this stuff.
So no, תנא כרבן שמעון בן גמליאל תנא קמיה. Tana k'Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel tana kmei. No, no, no, because he taught this idea
of מסדרין לבעל חוב mesadrin l'baal hov in the name of רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. And now it doesn't, רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel doesn't work with his own
position. הכי קאמר ליה, Hachi ka amar lei,
and this is what he's saying to him: השתא לרבן שמעון בן
גמליאל זבוני מזבנינן ליה, Hashta l'Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel zevunei mezavninan lei,
if רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel says that you can liquidate even his most basic
objects, his pillow, the things you're returning on a daily basis, when
it's time to pay the loan, סידורי מסדרינן ליה? sidurei mesadrinan lei?
So how can you tell me we have to leave stuff behind
when you're coming to pay the loan? דתנן, D'tnan, רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל אומר אף לעצמו אינו מחזיר אלא עד שלושים יום, מכאן ואילך
מוכרן בבית דין. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel omer af l'atzmo eino machazir
ela ad shloshim yom, mikan va'eilach mocharan b'veit din. Once thirty days
are up after defaulting on the loan, you know, then you can
liquidate even the most basic stuff. So how can רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel say מסדרין? mesadrin? How do you work
those two together? So the Gemara clearly is reading the מסדרין mesadrin
at the time of payment of the loan. So the Gemara says,
ומימה דכי קאמר רבן שמעון בן גמליאל זבוני לגמרי קאמר? U'mima d'chi
ka amar Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel zevunei legamrei ka amar? How do
you know when he says you can sell it, it means that
you sell it and don't leave the guy anything? There's ways you
can sell it and leave him something. Think about my idea about
the mansion. I have a ten-million-dollar mansion. Okay? You can sell it
to pay off my creditors and leave me homeless, or you can
sell it and pay off nine million dollars of the loan and
put me in a small little one-million-dollar place, right? So there's ways
you can sell it and still leave me something. So just because
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says you sell this
does not mean you don't leave the guy anything. ורמי, Verami, let's
read it, דילמא הכי קאמר. dilma hachi ka amar. Yeah, yeah, exactly.
I would get a half of a bedroom in the Upper West
Side. דילמא הכי קאמר: Dilma hachi ka amar: עד שלושים יום הדרה
בעיניה. ad shloshim yom hadra be'einei. For the first thirty days, return
the thing completely. מכאן ואילך מהדר ליה מאי דחזי ליה. Mikan va'eilach
mahader lei mai d'chazi lei. You give him something that is fit
for him, meaning that is, you know, will take care of his
basic needs, okay? ומזבנינן מאי דלא חזי ליה, U'mezavninan mai d'lo chazi
lei, and you sell the stuff that are not needed for his
basic needs, or you sell the fancy pillow and you buy him
a simpler pillow. Okay? Just because he's saying you start selling off
his property doesn't mean that you don't leave him anything, okay? You're
talking about a poor person in that case, not a rich person.
Right, and starting what kind of situation? Right, and starting what kind
of security even to begin with is there? It kind of reduces
it. Right, so there might be ways that the guy, that's what
real bankruptcy is, the guy has nothing and you're out, right? Because
once you're done leaving him his basic needs, you can't collect it
all. That's true. But okay, so the גמרא says, okay, אי סלקא
דעתך. Ei salka daitach. No, the גמרא says one minute. No, no,
no, that won't work. That's a nice answer. Yes, you could sell
stuff and leave him basic stuff, but it won't work with רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. Why won't it work with
רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel? אי סלקא דעתך איתא
לדרבי שמעון בן גמליאל האי סברא, Ei salka daitach ita l'derabi Shimon
ben Gamliel hai sevara, if רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben
Gamliel would say you sell but you have to leave him his
basic necessities, לית ליה מידי דלא חזי ליה, Leit leh midi d'lo
chazi leh, then there's nothing that is not fit for him, meaning
he could have a gorgeous golden bed with embroidered silk sheets and
I could say, I need this, this is my basic needs. Why
could he make that argument for רבן שמעון בן גמליאל? Rabban Shimon
ben Gamliel? דאמר אביי D'amar Abaye because אביי Abaye said, רבן שמעון
בן גמליאל ורבי שמעון ורבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא כולהו סבירא להו, Rabban
Shimon ben Gamliel v'Rabbi Shimon v'Rabbi Yishmael v'Rabbi Akiva kulehu sevira lehu,
all these four תנאים hold כל ישראל בני מלכים הן, Kol Yisrael
bnei melachim hein, that we treat things that happen for בני ישראל,
Bnei Yisrael, they're all descendants of אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov.
I don't know how that makes them בני מלכים, Bnei melachim, but
anyway, and they're all entitled to a very high standard of living
and a very high level of respect. So therefore, you would not
have a right to sell my hundred thousand dollar gold plated bed
and give me just a nice Sealy Posturepedic mattress. You need to
leave me my basic necessities. That's my basic necessity. Now, where do
you know that רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel says
this? רבן שמעון בן גמליאל דתנן: Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel d'tnan: לוף
וחרדל, Luf v'chardal, you cannot basically, let me just check רש"י here,
oh right, you cannot, these things are מוקצה. Muktzeh. לוף Luf is
a type of a, I don't know, of a gourd or something,
no, a type of a קטנית, Kitniyos, a type of a legume.
And חרדל Chardal is a mustard seed. So those are מוקצה Muktzeh
on שבת Shabbat because they can't be eaten. Mustard you'd have to
grind, mustard seed, and this קטנית Kitniyos you'd have to cook. So
they're מוקצה. Muktzeh. So you can't move them. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
מתיר בלוף. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel matir b'luf. No, no, no, לוף
Luf is not מוקצה. Muktzeh. Why? מפני שהוא מאכל לעורבין, Mipnei shehu
ma'achal l'orvin, because you can feed it to hawks or ravens. Now,
the fact because you know, I mean, princes, בני מלכים, Bnei melachim,
they have these hawks for pets, right? And they feed them stuff
and they go do hunting with their hawks. So even if you're
not a בן מלך, Ben melech, we're all בני מלכים Bnei melachim
and in theory we could all have ravens for pets. Okay. רבי
שמעון דתנן, Rabbi Shimon d'tnan, because we teach, בני מלכים סכין שמן
וורד על גבי מכותיהן בשבת. Bnei melachim sachin shemen v'vered al gabei
makoteihen b'Shabbat. On שבת, Shabbat, if you're actually like בני מלכים, Bnei
melachim, then you can put rose oil, rose water, whatever, rose oil
on your wounds on שבת Shabbat because you can't do things that
look like you're treating an illness. But בני מלכים Bnei melachim would
put this oil on their skin even for סתם purposes, you know,
just to anoint themselves for fragrance. So they can do it for
wounds as well and it's not obviously treating an illness, שכן דרכן
לסוך בחול, Sheken darkan lasuch b'chol, they would do that on a
weekday. רבי שמעון אומר כל ישראל בני מלכים הן. Rabbi Shimon omer
kol Yisrael bnei melachim hein. No, any Jew can do this because
they're all בני מלכים, Bnei melachim, so it's all considered something that's
appropriate for us. רבי ישמעאל ורבי עקיבא, Rabbi Yishmael v'Rabbi Akiva, okay,
so I guess we'll end here because it's already 8:30. But the
basic point is we'll see רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael and רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva in a minute that you would liquidate property in order
to pay off, leave the guy his basic needs, okay, and that
could work with רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, the combination of מסדרין Mesadrin
and of liquidating. But the problem is it can't work if a
guy is entitled to say that my basic necessities are these extreme
things. So therefore the גמרא doesn't understand how this could all work
with רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, okay, how you could ensure the guy
to leave something behind that's appropriate for him and at the same
time liquidate, in general that could work, and you could trade a
big house for a small house and a nice bed for a
not nice bed, but it can't work within רבן שמעון בן גמליאל
Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and this approach of בני מלכים. Bnei melachim.
All right, so we'll continue this tomorrow. It's a question of צדקה
Tzedakah and someone's כבוד, Kavod, right? So you have to, it's a
similar concept. All right, now we have to exit because Seth has
a class. And although none of your students are here, oh, they
are? Oh, we really have to exit, I'm sorry everybody. Let's get
out. Sometimes the גמרא would go in a direction of hairsplitting and
exactly, you know, what person gets what allotment and placement. Right. Right.
Yeah, I mean it does, but well, no, I mean because of
the בני מלכים Bnei melachim answer you mean? No, I think that
the...